בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ט. Chaf Tet. Yesterday
we—actually—excuse me כ"ד, Chaf Daled, excuse me. Today's דף daf is כ"ד.
Chaf Daled. Yesterday we discussed—or Michael Fein- was kind enough to substitute
and taught about the issues about כל נדרי. Kol Nidrei. We have
the answer—the issue about making a תנאי t'nai in your נדר. neder.
The משנה Mishnah spoke about the position of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov, who said that included in נדרי זירוזין, Nidrei
Zeruzin, the first example of נדרי זירוזין Nidrei Zeruzin was two people
haggling over the price of something and each of them making a
נדר neder what was like transparently obvious to everybody—that's redundant—transparent to everyone
that nobody was really serious about their vows, that was just part
of the haggling process. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov
then added to it a type of a way of making a
vow to get somebody to do something, but you never really wanted
that vow to be binding. You just wanted to use it as
pressure to get somebody to do something, making a vow so they
don't come to your house for dinner.
So that was רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Reminds
us of that story about אביי Abaye and his wife about sort
of making a vow as an ultimatum, but you never—problem with an
ultimatum is you gotta make good on it—but can you actually say
no, I really never wanted to make good on it? Anyway, so
that was רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabi Eliezer ben Yaakov, where it
wasn't necessarily transparently obvious to everybody, but at the end he was
really just using it as a type of a pressure and as
a leverage and he never would have wanted it to be binding.
But then there's also this mention about stipulating, making an explicit stipulation,
making it explicit that you're not serious about it. And the גמרא
Gemara identifies that as an independent statement, not that a case of
like just using a vow as pressure, as leverage, but actually making
a stipulation to prevent your vows from taking effect. But the גמרא—so
Gemara you stipulate at this—say, any vow I'm going to take later
I don't want it to be serious. So then the גמרא Gemara
sort of turns it on itself and says that—but if you—but if
you remember the vow—so that might work if you don't remember the
vows. So you're saying if I make a vow and I don't
remember that I had said now I don't want it to be
binding, I'm saying now I don't want it to be binding. Sort
of like giving a מודעה moda'ah that you can give even in
דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. If somebody is pressuring you to do something,
you can tell witnesses I'm being pressured to sell this plot of
land, even though I'm going to wind up signing the document, know
that I am not really selling this plot of land. So here
you can sort of—I mean it's not the exact same, but it's
analogous—say, if I forget, I really don't want to take vows this
year. I made a vow never to take another vow.
So anyway, so what I'm going to do is so I make
this stipulation. So then if I forget, then the stipulation defines that
I didn't want it to be binding. But—but the גמרא Gemara sort
of ironically says if you remember and you're vowing anyway, if you
didn't want it to be binding don't take the vow. If it's
a case that you're just not serious using it as leverage you
don't need the stipulation. If it's a normal vow, then don't take
it. So if you remember your condition and you're still making a
vow, that means that you want it to be binding. So by—אין
הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, if you remember the vow it's a
problem. רבא Rava gave a different answer which was like you half
remember the vow and therefore made a way in which—I don't want
to get into the specifics again, but some type of way where
if you sort of half remember the vow and then you remember
you can say it's based on that previous vow or not. But
he didn't really in a—besides that special case he—he did not in
principle really argue on אביי. Abaye. And bottom line what the גמרא
Gemara winds up saying is—is that somebody can take a vow at
the beginning of the year, ראש השנה—there's Rosh Hashanah no קידוש kiddush
at ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but means at the beginning of a
year, and so to say anything I'm going to do for the
rest of the year shouldn't be binding if I don't remember it.
And that's what we say by the way at the end of
the not כל נדרי, Kol Nidrei, but the end of the התרת
נדרים hatarat nedarim process. After you do התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you
say הריני מוסר מודעה לפניכם—there's hareini mosar moda'ah lifneichem that word
מודעה, moda'ah, proclamation and announcement—שכל נדר אשר shekol neder asher whatever שאדור
מהיום she'edor mehayom ולא יזכר—and—ולא את—what is it, what's the
language—הריהו מבוטל מעכשיו, hareihu mevutal me'achshav, right? And that is basically that's
the גמרא, Gemara, making a proclamation at the beginning of the year
as I'll let you know that anything I say in the future
should not be binding, period. The reality is that if that really
worked you wouldn't have to do a התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim the
next year. You'd only have to do like התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim
every other year or something. You just would have to repeat the
מודעה moda'ah and then you would never have to do התרת נדרים.
hatarat nedarim. But that's really the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. And then the
ר"ן Ran discusses the issue about how does this play out with
כל נדרי. Kol Nidrei. כל נדרי Kol Nidrei is—and in a way
you could also ask how does it play out with the התרת
נדרים hatarat nedarim that we do on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Where
התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim is usually like—so that seems to be past
oriented. If I made a נדר neder and I didn't—to keep it,
we're now going to do a התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. Okay? And
in the same way the התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim that you do
on ערב ראש השנה erev Rosh Hashanah is a type of a
generic one, right, you're not really saying exactly why it is that
you would not have taken it. As we've learned, if you just
say חרטה, charatah, okay, I regret it. You don't need a specific
פתח, petach, right? So you just say I regret having made it,
end of story. Okay. So we can do a... a generic one
for you as an individual, that's חרטה, charata, not פתח. petach. And
we can do a generic one for the whole ציבור, tzibur, you
know, that hey, hey everybody, if anybody out here the whole ציבור
tzibur has made a נדר, neder, now that's an interesting question: Can
you do it without the person presenting him or herself, you know,
and being asked, are you מתחרט, mischarait, right? Just sort of making
a declaration, any נדר neder made, we're saying that, you know, if
people are מתחרט, mischarait, we're sort of annulling. So that's why כל
נדרי Kol Nidrei is a little bit strange because obviously you're not
doing it yourself. It really plays out the past and the future
in the התרת נדרים, Hataras Nedarim, and that really combines the two
discussions we've been having in the גמרא. Gemara. And the התרת נדרים
Hataras Nedarim has explicitly both of them, right? מתיר matir the past
based on a sort of generic חרטה charata and take a condition
for the future. Whereas the כל נדרי Kol Nidrei is like, it's
not, it doesn't, you know, you know what people say the real
meaning of כל נדרי Kol Nidrei is the ניגון? nigun? You know,
that like, you know, the ניגון, nigun, meaning it's the, you know,
it's the emotional experience it brings you into. ספרדים Sefardim don't do
כל נדרי, Kol Nidrei, do they?
No, התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim sometime between ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
But they don't do a כל נדרי Kol Nidrei on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur night. No, they don't. And you know, Rav Hirsch got
rid of the כל נדרי Kol Nidrei because Jews for many, and
it, I'm not, I don't know the exact history, but there were
definitely periods of time where
Jews
got in a lot of trouble for כל נדרי Kol Nidrei because
basically the way you would sort
of back up the integrity of a business deal or your honesty
in your dealings with non-Jews, as we've been saying, was to take
a vow. Well, great, the Jews take a vow and then they
turn around on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and they go and they
get themselves out of their vows. So, you know, they're just lying
and scheming and they're really releasing themselves from their vows and so
on. So Hirsch did away with כל נדרי. Kol Nidrei. Rav Hirsch
did away with כל נדרי. Kol Nidrei. And it does raise, you
know, and there's a real question like what halachic meaning it has,
because again, you're not making the stipulation, you're not presenting yourself, you're
not doing the התרת נדרים. Hataras Nedarim. And then the other question
is, right, does it refer to the past or to the future?
And the simple sense is that it refers to the past, but
רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam wanted to make it based on this, maybe
because of this sensibility, not clear why, wanted to make it based
on the future and therefore had to switch some of the grammar
of it to make it based on the future. Now some of
the מחזורים machzorim have two נוסחאות, nuschaos, a past נוסח nusach and
a future נוסח, nusach, and sometimes they have both of them in
the same, sometimes they say as different versions, you know, you could
say version A or version B. I sent out an article for
anybody that's interested by Dr. Richard Steiner on the grammar of כל
נדרי Kol Nidrei based on whether it's past or future, so enjoy
reading that.
Okay, so now, so
now we pick up, I've done so well on my biblical grammar,
I'm ready to move on to technical Aramaic grammar. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. So now they raise a question, two lines
down from the bottom of the wide lines. I mean, from the
bottom of the page. What?
גמרא's Gemara in אלה דהוה דריש בפרקא? ela dehavah darish bepirka?
Okay, you want to start from that? Yes, התרת נדרים. Hataras Nedarim.
Okay, fine. Okay, רב הונא בר חיננא Rav Huna bar Chinana סבר
למידרשיה בפרקא. savar lemidrashye bepirka.
So, okay, I'm sorry. רב הונא בר חיננא Rav
Huna bar Chinana סבר
למידרשיה בפרקא.
savar lemidrashye bepirka.
So he wanted to make this announcement out in the marketplace that,
you know, or whatever, not the פרקא, pirka, the marketplace, whatever, you
know, when everybody was gathered, to tell them you can make a
stipulation and get yourself out of these נדרים. nedarim. אמר ליה רבא.
Amar lei Rava. So Rava said, תנא קא מסתם לה סתומי. Tana
ka mistam lei satumei.
Our תנא Tana sort of made it, like, hid the information because
it sort of, it sort of like, you know,
melded this case into the one about the נדרי זרוזין nedrei zeruzin
about the guy that's trying to get his friend to come over
for dinner. So it wasn't explicit about this idea of making a
generic תנאי. tnai. So our תנא Tana was sort of more subtle
about it, hidden about it, כדי שלא ינהגו קלות ראש בנדרים, kedei
shelo yinhagu kalos rosh benedarim, so people shouldn't just say, oh, let
me just make a תנאי tnai and then I don't have to
worry about any נדר neder I make. So that's why it was,
the information was hidden in our משנה. mishna. ואת דרשת לה בפרקא?
V'at darshet lah bepirka?
And you're now going to publicize it? So this, of course, raises,
this is a fascinating statement for two reasons. Well, number one, first
of all, the ר"ן Ran said, therefore, the ר"ן Ran says that
he can't believe that כל נדרי Kol Nidrei is future-oriented if the
whole גמרא Gemara here has a point about not making too much
of a public aspect of it. Okay, fine. That's, okay, that's an
interesting point about factoring into what you think כל נדרי's Kol Nidrei
about. But what's also interesting about this is, you know, when the
גמרא Gemara does a reread of the משנה, mishna, let's be honest,
the simple sense of the משנה mishna is not two הלכות. halachos.
It's that you're trying to get your friend to eat by you
and you make a נדר neder based on a תנאי tnai that
you have, you know, stipulated that you're not going to be serious.
The גמרא Gemara broke it up into two different cases. One is
just making a נדר neder to get him to eat by you
is נדרי זרוזין, nedrei zeruzin, and the other is an idea of
תנאי. tnai. So when we read those types of rereads of the
משנה, mishna, right, we tend to think that, like, we tend to
wonder, did the גמרא Gemara really think that was פשט? pshat? Or,
you know, is the גמרא Gemara just saying, it doesn't really matter
if it's פשט, pshat, this is what we, you know, this is
what conforms to our understanding of what the הלכה halacha has to
be? So here it's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara actually thought it
was פשט. pshat. It's saying, like, the fact that this information was
hidden in the משנה mishna and we had to sort of go,
you know, sort of dig it out. you know, shows that this
is a like a principle we shouldn't be publicizing. So number one
is just fascinating that it reflects, again, not all the time, but
that when the גמרא Gemara sometimes does a re-read of the משנה,
Mishnah, it really thinks it's פשט. pshat. It thinks it's like a
פשט pshat that just had to be explicated. Number one. Number two
is the idea of, you know, this issue of transparency in terms
of פסק הלכה psak halacha where like you take like this, you
know, as opposed to maybe a more sort of paternal or, you
know, paternalistic approach, like, you know, you know, you know, like you
can't handle the truth. I have to protect, you know, I'm not
going to tell you everything. I'm going to only, I'm not going
to necessarily always be fully transparent about what the הלכה halacha is
because if I am fully transparent, you know, then that might lead
you to make, you know, to to accidentally sin because I, you
know, because you'll be sloppy about certain things. You know, so it's
like sometimes the גמרא Gemara has a principle like הלכה ואין מורין
כן; halacha v'ein morin kein; it is the הלכה halacha but I'm
not going to publicize it and tell people about it, you know,
and sometimes in those handbooks that come out, those English handbooks, they
do this by the English on the top is what they want
to tell the public, and then the footnotes in Hebrew at the
bottom is for people that are תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that they
can trust with the information.
You only told them what you're going to really? Exactly.
The only problem with that is when you the that for in
Israel, you can't have, you know, the the facility with language doesn't
divide the two classes of people, so it doesn't always work. Anyway,
so this is interesting in terms of that.
Okay, so what on the other hand, what what did רב הונא
בר חיננא Rav Huna bar Chinana actually what does the מדרש midrash
say of the פירקא, pirka, he
was in the בית מדרש? beis medrash? Yeah, and the פירקא pirka
is also like yeah when like, you know, people are gathered, you
know, right. And he wanted to make a public announcement. Everybody should
be aware there's a great way you can save yourself from being
נכשל בנדרים. nichshal b'nedarim. Just make this stipulation on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah or whatever. And רבא Rava says no, that actually will lead
to more sloppiness by נדרים, nedarim, you know, and you should have
learned from our משנה Mishnah that you don't go ahead
to say Right.
Right. Now actually, what's interesting about this, and again, this is an
ongoing also tension that we've seen in our מסכת, masechet, which is
an ongoing tension in life, which is, do you want to save
people from sin or do you want to but if you sort
of make it too easy, if you've given them a way that
they're not going to transgress the נדרים nedarim they make, oh, that's
really not binding, that's really not binding, why don't you stipulate, etc.,
then it just encourages sloppiness in their behavior, right? Remember so we've
seen that like sometimes the נדר neder really isn't binding but we
make somebody go through hoops to do a to be released from
it in order that they're not overly sloppy, and also differences between
like תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and non-תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, right? And
there's all these different this ongoing has been the issue about if
you make it not binding then the person won't transgress, but maybe
you're encouraging sloppiness. So that's also what's going on here. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: איבעיא להו. Iba'e'u lehu. So they
raise the following question. פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב או
לא? Pligi rabanan alei d'Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov o lo? Did the
rabbis disagree with רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov or
not? Now we're putting aside the תנאי tnai issue. The גמרא Gemara
assumes interestingly that if the even if the תנאי tnai was in
the משנה Mishnah as a separate thing, everybody would agree to that,
right? Because here you see the גמרא Gemara just said, yeah, you
can make a תנאי tnai at the beginning on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah etc. So what actually is the question is not the תנאי
tnai part but the but the נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin part about
קמיבעיא ליה. kamiba'aya lei. I want you to have dinner by me.
If you don't have dinner by me, then all of your food
is אסור עלי, assur alai, right? Or all of my food is
אסור assur to you. So it's a lit it's different than the
haggling. The haggling like everybody knew they were engaging in a game
and nobody was serious. Right? Here you might actually think that I
am being serious, but I really don't want to make the נדר
neder and there was never a הוה אמינא havah amina that I
would have wanted the נדר neder to be חל chal even had
even if you didn't accept, but I was doing it to pressure
you, okay, or to encourage you. Okay, so do the and that's
נדרי זירוזין. nidrei zeruzin. Maybe no, maybe since it's less transparent and
obvious and maybe somebody actually there are people out there that actually
would be offended if you don't come to my house, I will
be so offended, I'm going to take such a personal slight that
I never want you to be נהנה neheneh from anything of mine
again. You could imagine somebody like that. So maybe that is sincere,
maybe it's not נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin or you know, so maybe
the rabbis don't agree to call that נדרי זירוזין. nidrei zeruzin. Alright?
So תא שמע, tasha shma, so do the rabbis agree or disagree?
ואם תימצא לומר פליגי, Ve'im timtza lomar pligi, if they do disagree,
הלכתא כוותיה או לא? hilchata kevasei o lo? Do we rule like
it or not? Do we rule like the rabbis or do we
rule like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב? Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov? All right,
so when it's not this game of haggling in two-sided, it's one-sided
and it could possibly be sincere but it wasn't intended that way,
is that נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin or not? תא שמע, Tasha shma,
come and hear, תנן. tnan. אומר לחבירו, Omer lechavero, somebody who says
to his friend: קונם שאני נהנה לך אם אי אתה נוטל לבנך
כור של חטים ושתי חביות
של יין. Konam she'ani neheneh lecha im i attah notel livnecha koresh
chitin ushtei chaviyot shel yayin. So קונם, konam, it says שאני, she'ani,
not שאיני, she'eini, but okay. I will not derive or all of
your stuff is forbidden on me to get benefit from if you
don't accept this gift that I'm trying to give to your sons.
I want to give to your sons this nice basket of wheat
and two barrels of wine, you know, I don't know, maybe you
just had a wedding, I want to give it as a wedding
present, okay, and you don't want to accept, you say no, no,
no, please, please, don't, you know, it's okay, you don't have to
give me anything. So in the middle of that type of maybe
friendly haggling or whatever or friendly, you know, I don't know, exchange...
I say if you don't take this gift that I'm trying to
give to your sons, then I'll never get any benefit from you.
All your stuff will be קונם konam to me. הרי זה יכול
להתיר נדרו. harei ze yachol lehatir nidro.
So I can get a היתר heter to my נדר. neder. Why?
שלא פי חכם, shelo pi chacham, even without asking a חכם, chacham,
meaning the נדר neder isn't binding. שיכול לומר לו כלום אמרת אלא
בשביל כבודי זהו כבודי, sheyachol lomar lo klum amarta ela bishvil kvodi
zehu kvodi,
because now even if the guy says I won't accept it, so
I said if you don't accept it your stuff is forbidden to
me. So now why isn't your stuff forbidden to me? Because basically
in theory the guy could say back, he could say, look, why
did you want me to accept it? You wanted to accept it
because you wanted to honor me by giving me a gift. I
am telling you that it is more honor to me or just
as much, maybe even more honor for me for me to refuse
a gift, right? So that's the fact that you offered me a
gift and I refused it, like oh I'm so חשיב, chashuv, I
don't even have to accept gifts. So I got all the honor
you wanted to give to me. So therefore you don't have to
feel like, you know, what you were trying to achieve was ultimately
achieved. Ultimately you didn't care about giving me the gift; you wanted
to give me an honor, right? So I got the honor that
you made me that offer and that I refused it.
Yes, that's interesting. I don't think we've seen this before. This is
not like—it's not זירוזין. zeruzin. It's
you were sincere when you made that נדר, neder, but let me
clarify because you're really wrong.
Right. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to prove. You
see it's not נדרי זירוזין. nidrei zeruzin. The only reason it's not
binding is because the תנאי tnai was actually satisfied. It's like he
accepted it. Right. So that's what the גמרא's Gemara's point is.
Right.
What? There's some lack of graciousness in this response. Right.
He's saying you're honoring me but in effect he's dishonoring the person
who's wanting to give the gift in
a sense by not allowing him to give the gift. Right, exactly.
And you know the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says something about that. The ירושלמי
Yerushalmi says what made you think that when I was giving a
gift to you I only cared about honoring you? You know it
was also like it was an honor to me that I was
able—it meant something to me that I was able to give a
gift to you. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says this. The ירושלמי
Yerushalmi says if the guy says back no I made the תנאי
tnai not לכבודך lechvodecha but לכבודי. lechvodi. I wanted you to accept
it because I—it concerned me, I wanted it, not for—not for you,
I wanted it for me for you to accept the gift. Then
it says okay then you're stuck, then the נדר neder is binding.
But if we—the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually exactly says that. Now the question
is what if it's not clear and explicit for whose honor it
was, okay? But that's at least what—yeah.
But those responses don't really address the point of what a mutual
exchange might have in other words that there's acceptance of some kind
of—there could be in some situations some kind of a love of
giving to both sides and those two responses just point to one
or the other as something that—right, right.
And look, it also might be based on the, you know, in
the Roman world—and I learned this many years ago and I'm forgetting
the details—but the whole system of patronage was very much, you know,
not just about like a friendly gift, but it really was this
thing. Like if you're willing to accept—like, you know, we have this
משנה Mishnah in קידושין Kiddushin that one way you could be מקדש
אישה mekadesh isha is if you say—if it says דהיא—that de'hi if
the woman gives the gift something to the man, and it's with
that הנאה hana'ah that you agree to accept my gift. So in
a world of patronage if you are in a more important political,
you know, power position and I give you a gift and you
agree to accept it, that actually is a very powerful statement, right?
So that—so there's something here that's not necessarily just
about—could be not necessarily just about two friends. Okay.
So anyway זהו כבודי, zehu kvodi, this is my honor that you
offered it and then I refused it. So your—so actually it was
satisfied, as if your gift was—as if your desire were fulfilled, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says הלאו הכי טעמא דאמר זהו כבודי. halav
hachi ta'ama de'amar zehu kvodi.
The reason that the נדר neder isn't binding is because it's effectively
as if he accepted it because he was honored regardless. הלאו הכי,
halav hachi, if it weren't for that reason, נדר, neder, it would
be a נדר neder even though he's just trying to get him
to accept the gift. So you see when it's not that—when it's
used as a way to pressure somebody to accept something, you know,
it really is a נדר; neder; it's not נדרי זירוזין. nidrei zeruzin.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I mean if it's not again one
of those more transparent cases like the haggling. So the
גמרא Gemara says no הא מני, ha mani, so who is this
going like? אי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, ei Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
if it's רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, נדרי זירוזין
הוי. nidrei zeruzin havai. So this
is—so this is נדרי זירוזין; nidrei zeruzin; it should not be binding
because you just said it's a נדר neder because you wanted him
to accept your gift, like a נדר neder like you wanted a
guy to come have dinner by you. אלא שמע מינה פליגי רבנן
עליה, ela shma mina pligi rabbanan alei, it must be the רבנן.
rabbanan. The רבנן rabbanan must be arguing on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and say that this type of a thing
is not נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin and it is binding. So that's
a pretty good proof, right? That was what Rabbi Dov you were
saying. It says no לעולם רבי אליעזר בן יעקב הוא. le'olam Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov hu. It could really be רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that says that normally if I say my
food is forbidden to you, you know, קונם konam my stuff on
you if you don't come for dinner, he could still agree in
this case about receiving the gift. Why?
מודה רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
בהאי דנדרא הוי. modeh Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov be'hai denidra havai. This
say is a נדר, neder, is not just זירוזין. ziruzin. דאמר ליה
d'amar lei because I say to the guy who I'm trying to
give the gift to, לא כלבא אנא, lo kalba ana, I'm not
like a dog, דמיתהנינא מינך d'mit'hanina minech that I would get benefit
from you, ולא מיתהנית מינאי, v'lo mit'hanita minai, and you wouldn't get
benefit from me, meaning here's the difference. The difference says when I
come to invite you to dinner and I say if you don't
come to have dinner for me then all my food is forbidden
to you, so basically that might really be sincere, like I am
so piqued
at your slight to me that you wouldn't take this from me,
I never want you to be able to take anything from me.
Right? So that might be because I'm angry and upset at you,
etc. But here there's a different dynamic going on. I'm sorry, did
I say that wrong? I said that wrong. I made that one
more weighty. Okay, forget that. But anyway, in that case, it's if
you don't come to me then my stuff is forbidden to you.
It's all one direction. You won't get stuff from me, right? In
this case, it's the reverse. It's if
you won't accept this from me,
then I won't get benefit from your stuff. So basically, what the
גמרא Gemara is saying here is that this case could be more
binding because the guy could be more sincere about
this, like if I would never
get any benefit from you if you won't get any benefit from
me, like saying sincerely, I don't want to have that type of
a relationship. You're always doing favors for me, and I'm never doing
any favors for you, and you're never receiving any favors from me.
So somebody could be sincere that they don't want a relationship like
that. If you won't accept this, then I can't see how I
could ever take anything from you. All right? So that could be
more sincere than if you don't come to me for dinner then
my food is forbidden to you, which might just be more of
a hollow threat and not really too sincere. Okay, so that's why
it's different.
By the way, I'll just say parenthetically, what I just said is
how the ר"ן Ran explains it, and it works very well in
the cases and in the language of the גמרא. Gemara. But the
רשב"א Rashba reads this differently. The רשב"א Rashba reads the reason here
it's more sincere is just because here we're talking about a very
serious gift and not about just like a courtesy. Like if I'm
just inviting you for dinner, of course I'm not so serious. Why
would I get so upset that you don't want to come to
dinner? If we're talking about a much more serious gift, then something
more weighty, then I could be much more sincere that I wanted
it to be a נדר. neder. Okay, but that doesn't really reflect
the language of the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara never points to
how big of a gift it is or how big of the
thing is. The language really reflects what the ר"ן Ran is saying.
If I say if you don't come to dinner then you won't
get benefit from me, maybe I'm just using it as an empty
threat. Whereas if I say if you don't accept this from me,
I won't get benefit from you, that's an issue about reciprocity. That's
an issue about that type of a dynamic is not a dynamic
I want, and therefore I might much more be sincere.
Every time I invite you for שבת, Shabbat, you say oh, come
and join us at our... exactly. It's an empty feeling at a
certain... exactly.
Exactly. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. האומר לחברו קונם שאתה
נהנית לי אם אי אתה נותן לבני כור של חטים ושתי חביות
של יין. ha'omer l'chavero konam she'ata nehenit li im ee ata noten
livni kor shel chitin u'shtei chavyot shel yayin. Okay,
the
opposite. Basically I say now I'm the one who has married off
my son or whatever, my son's birthday, and I say to Michael
there, I say Michael, you cannot get any benefit from me if
you don't give my son a birthday gift. Okay? So, and by
the way, what he has eyes set on is a LEGO set
of two barrels of wine
and a basket full of grain.
Okay, real wine and grain is less expensive than the LEGO.
Okay, anyway, so רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbe Meir omer, okay, so רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir says עד שיתן. ad sheyiten. So until
Michael, you give my son that gift, then you can't get any
benefit from me, right? Because my stuff, I said my stuff is
forbidden unless you give my son this gift. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim,
and the חכמים Chachamim say אף זה יכול להתיר את נדרו. af
zeh yakhol l'hatir et nidro.
No, even here, you know Michael, you can get out of it,
בלא פי חכם, b'lo pi chacham, without a חכם. chacham. Well, I
made the vow, but okay, that's the question who would transgress. Anyway,
we can get out of the vow, שיכול לומר, sheyakhol lomar,
you're right, it is talking about me, שיכול לומר הריני כאילו התקבלתי.
sheyakhol lomar hareni k'ilu hitkabalti. Because I could say to Michael, you
know what?
It's okay. It's like, you know, you're so nice in general, it's
like we got the gift from you. Okay, so that's similar to
although the תנאי tnai wasn't met, it's as if the תנאי tnai
was met. In one case, the purpose of the תנאי tnai was
to give honor, and I could say it's like I received that
honor. In this case, I wanted a gift, but I say it's
like I received that gift. Okay, now before we get to this
issue of נדרי זירוזין, nidrei ziruzin, the ר"ן Ran wants to know
what does that mean you could say it's as if I received
that gift? So he says there's a way, there's one possible understanding,
which is what we're only talking about when it's actually to do
something for me and to give me something because here's what could
have happened. Michael could have gone ahead and given me the barrels
of wine, and I could have said, you know what Michael, it's
okay, take it back. So it's, and I therefore even without giving
it to me, I could say we'll pretend that's what happened. We'll
pretend you gave it to me and I gave it back to
you. Okay. Right? So then I could say I'll treat it as
if it actually happened. But let's say I said something different to
Michael, let's say I said קונם Konam this is אסור asur to
me unless you I don't know I'm really concerned about your health
there Michael, so קונם Konam this is אסור asur to you unless
you actually start going to the gym two times a week. Okay,
and he doesn't go to the gym two times a week. Could
I say well it's כאילו התקבלתי? ke'ilu hikbalti? What does that mean,
כאילו התקבלתי? ke'ilu hikbalti? Right? It's like, you know, it's not anything
about me receiving and giving back, I just have the option of
saying I waive my תנאי, tnai, essentially it's a way of saying
like I'll pretend as if you fulfilled it. Is that really like
a type of a generic option? Okay, so that's, you know, that's
a lot now there's some middle case where Michael does something to
me but it's not an object like, you know, I'll say like
my stuff is forbidden to me unless you, I don't know, come
and have dinner with me, right? And then I would say well
כאילו ke'ilu which is sort of like what we've been talking about,
right? Why can't I say and say well you didn't have dinner
with me but it's like כאילו התקבלתי, ke'ilu hikbalti, it's as if
you had dinner with me. What do you mean as if? Right?
How can you just say I'll pretend as if? So the הר"ן,
Ran, so there's the הר"ן Ran raises this discussion. He says it's
a lot easier to say I'll pretend as if when we're talking
about giving an object. I wanted you to give me an object,
we'll pretend like you gave me the object and I gave it
back to you or to give me money I'll pretend you gave
me the money I gave it back to you. But if it's
I wanted you to do some activity or certainly if it's not
even an activity you're doing for me, just some other type of
a thing, right? Then how could I say how do I can
I say it's as if it happened? On the other hand he
says no, maybe if you make the תנאי, tnai, at the end
of the day, the purpose of the תנאי tnai is you want
your desire satisfied so in a way you could always say you
know what, it's good enough, like it's ultimately rooted in something you
wanted and therefore you can essentially say I'll treat it as if
it happened, which is another I think way of just saying I'll
waive the תנאי, tnai, you know, sort of like I'll pretend as
if yeah.
Isn't there also motivational aspect?
What? Well that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to get to. But
before we get to the נדרי זירוזין, nidrei zeruzin, right, that's the
whole point of the גמרא. Gemara. It doesn't sound like it's נדרי
זירוזין, nidrei zeruzin, this says it's a real נדר, neder, but the
only question was was the תנאי tnai satisfied or not. So first
we're dealing with what makes it considered as if the תנאי tnai
was satisfied.
Okay, so now you indicated the example you gave about Michael going
to the gym. Right. That's just your motivation.
Right, well that's essentially what the גמרא's Gemara going to get to.
Okay, so but the first point was was that fundamentally this is
a binding תנאי, tnai, okay, if you say like your you know
my stuff is אסור asur unless you give my son a gift,
but there's a way out of it because you could say it's
like I got the gift, כאילו, ke'ilu, right, כאילו התקבלתי. ke'ilu hikbalti.
הלא
הכי נדר הוא, halavachi neder hu, but without that as if I
received the gift, if you just said, if you don't, you know,
if you don't if you couldn't say that it was like a
כאילו, ke'ilu, then it would be a would be binding
הוא. hu.
נדר הוא. neder hu. מני? mani? Who's this according to? אי רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב, iy Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, נדרי זירוזין הוי, nidrei
zeruzin havei, it's just נדרי זירוזין, nidrei zeruzin, I'm just trying to
pressure Michael to give my son a gift, הוי. havei. אלא לאו
רבנן, ela lav rabbanan, it must be the Rabbis, ופליגי, u-pligi, so
you see the Rabbis argue on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov, they say that when it's not again this transparent case
of haggling, a נדר neder used to pressure somebody like this really
is a נדר. neder. Okay? Because I was just trying to pressure
Michael to give the gift.
גמרא Gemara says you literally say
כאילו התקבלתי, ke'ilu hikbalti, right? Is he saying it or is it
type of a legal like, you know, as if I'm sort of
imposing that logic?
That's a good question. It sounds like he has to say it.
Yeah, he does, because right,
simple way of reading
it, yeah, it definitely says so. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this: לא. lo. לעולם רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, le-olam Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov, it really is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov,
ומודה רבי אליעזר בהא, u-modei Rabbi Eliezer behai, even the רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer who would normally say that a vow to pressure is
a נדרי זירוזין, nidrei zeruzin, here he would say it's serious. Why?
דנדרא הוי, de-nidra havei, that it is a נדר, neder, משום דאמר
ליה mishum de-amar lei because I would say to Michael, look, רב
מלכא אנא, rav malka ana, I what who do you think I
am? You think I'm Rockefeller? You think I'm a king?
Which would go to a king, that's the point. דמהנינא לך, de-mahnina
lakh, I could give you, you know, some I you know I
could give you benefit, I could, you know, I could be nice
to you, ואת לא מהנית לי, ve-at la mahnit li, and you
would never have to do anything in, you know, to for me?
Like what is it you, you know, you expect I'm Daddy Warbucks
or something? So, you like
my substitutes for king? Okay, anyway, so
what was that story? Whatever I won't go there. Anyway, so there
was something about this that like I don't know one of Rockefeller's
kids,
some poor person came to Rockefeller and asked him who was the
father of the family
people remember? Anyway whatever. Asked him for a
donation and
he gave him
like some small amount so he says, you know, when I asked
your son for a donation like he gave me like a whatever
a hundred dollars. And the father says, well he can afford to,
he's got a rich father.
So anyway, alright, so
the גמרא Gemara says רב מלכא
אנא,
rav malka
ana, so anyway. Therefore, what's the point? The point is, I say
to Michael, I'm serious about it, Michael. You know, I've given your
sons' birthday presents, so if you don't go ahead and give my
son a birthday present,
you'll never get any benefit from me. What type of relationship is
that, that you're not going to give my son a birthday present
and you're going to expect me to give yours? So if you
don't do it, then I'm serious, I don't want you to get
any benefit. So because this is not, the case in the משנה
Mishna is, right, if you don't come to me for dinner, my
food is going to be forbidden for you. It's not the reciprocal.
It's the same direction. If you don't take my dinner now, my
food will be forbidden to you. That maybe is זרוזין. zruzin. When
it's in the opposite direction, if you don't take this from me
then I won't take anything from you, or if you don't give
me something then I won't give you something, that maybe is serious
because that's what type we want, what type of relationship would this
be? So that might be a case that even רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov would agree to, so it doesn't prove
that there's a חכמים Chachamim out there that argue on רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב. Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי. Amar lei Mar
Kashisha brei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi. So the elder מר קשישא, Mar
Kashisha, the son of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, said to רב אשי:
Rav Ashi: תא שמע, Ta shma, let's try again. Let's try this.
נדרי אונסין. Nidrei Onsin. So here's the case what we're coming up
in a later משנה Mishna about remember there are four types of
נדרים nedarim that are not binding, right? So we've dealt with נדרי
זרוזין. Nidrei Zruzin. Now we're going to get to נדרי אונסין. Nidrei
Onsin. What's נדרי אונסין? Nidrei Onsin? Out of your control. Here's what
it is. הדירו חבירו שיאכל אצלו וחלה הוא. Hidira chaveiro sheyochal etzlo
v'chalahu.
So I basically, again this case, I say, Michael, if you don't
come and have dinner with me then my food is forbidden to
you. Okay, and Michael was on his way to come and have
dinner with me, but he got sick, או חלה בנו, o chala
beno, or his son got sick, או עיכבו נהר, o sikvo nahara,
or a river passed through and he couldn't cross the river, whatever,
it got flooded or something. So therefore the vow isn't binding because
there was a desire to fulfill the תנאי tnai which would have
prevented the vow from being binding that was not fulfilled because of
an אונס. ones. So therefore I never expected, here's a way of
saying it, I never expected the vow to be binding if you
made your best effort and still weren't able to do it, right?
I made the vow because I wanted you to come, but at
the end of the day what I really wanted you to do
was to make your best effort to come and therefore I never
would have wanted it in this situation. Okay, but that's אונס. ones.
So the condition that I was making focusing on would have been
fulfilled
were it not for the אונס ones part. If you just chose
not to come, the vow would be binding. But this sounds like
נדרי זרוזין. Nidrei Zruzin. This is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב's Rebbe Eliezer
ben Yaakov case. If you don't come to dinner, my food is
forbidden to you. So isn't that a נדרי זרוזין Nidrei Zruzin and
it still sounds like it's binding? So you see the Rabbis argue
on רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov.
Yes, Dov, is there a concern with evaluating
the sincerity or authenticity of an אונס ones case? In other words,
I'll be there for dinner in fifteen minutes, it's five o'clock, I
have to go to the West Side, but everybody knows the traffic
is bad.
All right, so let's hold that off until we get to that
משנה, Mishna, okay? Because נדרי אונסין Nidrei Onsin is coming up. But
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: התם הוא. Hasam hu. הלא הכי נדר
הוא. hala hachi neder hu. So the גמרא Gemara says, were it
not for that, נדר הוא, neder hu, it's a נדר neder because
even though it says if you don't eat by me and my
food is forbidden, if you willfully chose not to come to dinner
it would be binding. מאני, Mani, who is this like? רבי אליעזר
בן יעקב זרוזין הוי? Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov zruzin navei? Couldn't רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב, Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov, that's a type of a
זרוזין, zruzin, it's a one-directional used to encourage somebody. אלא רבנן היא,
Ella Rabbanan hi, it must be the Rabbis who פליגי peligi and
you see the Rabbis argue, you see there's a position that says
that a נדר neder is binding in this case. It says no,
לעולם רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, l'olam Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov, it is
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב. Rebbe Eliezer ben Yaakov. ומי סברת דאדרי מזמנא
לזמינא? Umi svarta d'adrei mizamna l'zamina? What makes you think that the
vow was initiated by the inviter and done against the invitee? No,
that's not the case, it's the opposite.
דזמינא אדרי למזמנא. dizamina adrei l'mizamna. The
invitee initiated the vow with the inviter. What happened? דאמר ליה, d'amar
lei, because Michael's been dying to have dinner by me and I've
been avoiding him. So he says to me: מזמנת לי לסעודתך? Mizamta
li l'seudataich? Come on Dov, will you finally have me over for
dinner? אמר ליה אין, Amar lei in, I say fine, okay, yes,
you forced my hand. נדר זה עליך. Neder zeh aleicha. So Michael
says I don't trust you, take a vow that if you don't
invite, I'm sorry, no, אמר ליה אין נדר זה עליך, Amar lei
in neder zeh aleicha, I still have to do that to Michael,
excuse me. And I, no, so Michael says,
Dov, I think you've been avoiding me, you don't really want to
have me to dinner, I really would love to come to dinner,
and I say of course I want to have you to dinner,
I'll show how sincere I am that I'm going to, if you
don't come to dinner for me all my food should be forbidden
to you. It's an odd vow, but anyway, but it started somehow
with Michael initiating it. Okay, אין, in, yes, נדר זה עליך neder
zeh aleicha and I'll even make a vow on you that I'm
so much invested in you coming that I will make a vow
that my food is forbidden to you if you don't come. Okay,
ונדר, u'nadar, and I made a vow. Or Michael again, I might
have misread it again. It might have been Michael said נדר זילך,
neder zilecha, make a vow, ונדר, v'nadar, and then I made the
vow. Okay. Anyway, he was the initiator of the whole thing. וחלה
הוא או שחלה בנו או שעיקבו חום v'khala hu o she-khala beno
o she-ikevo khom and then in the end he couldn't come so
because of some אונס, ones, הרי אלו נדרי אונסין. harei elu nidrei
onsin. Then it's not binding. Now why is this different? Because then
it's not נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin because I'm not making the vow
to you know to sort of to force Michael's hand. Michael was
the initiator. He wanted to come for dinner. He just told me
make a vow to show me that you're sincere. Okay. So in
the end of the day so that's not נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin
because it was clear that Michael was coming, I did not need
it to force his hand. Now maybe you could say then it
should be a vow for another reason. I don't know why, I
still wasn't sincere because I was just doing it to make him
happy, but nevertheless, okay, it's not the same case. It's not done
just to you know pressure somebody to get a result. So we
still don't have the answer. All of the evidence is definitely pointing
to the fact that there's a stricter position out there that these
cases are real נדרים, nedarim, but the גמרא Gemara has a way
to make them special cases. Either that it was the other person
initiated or there was some reciprocity going on here, but anyway there
does seem to be a lot of evidence that these types of
vows are binding.
But in the cases we say it's you know it's that we
said that יכול להתיר בלא פי חכם, yakhol l'hattir belo pi khakham,
that's almost like just a pulse step away from saying it's not
a נדר, neder, right?
But that's in the special case where it's possible to say התקבלתי
או זהו כבודי. hitkabalti o zehu kevodi. You're not always able to
say that like okay
so right yes but I guess the question is this. Do we
make it you know sort of to התקבלתי hitkabalti kind of thing,
you know what I mean?
No, but not all cases can you say that, like the ר"ן
Ran discusses cases where you can't say התקבלתי. hitkabalti. Okay. תא שמע.
ta shema. יתר על כן אמר רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. yeter al
ken amar Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov went further, okay, not just to the case about if
you don't come to dinner. And he said the following. האומר לחבירו
קונם שאני נהנה לך אם אי אתה מתארח אצלי ותאכל עמי פת
חמה ותשתה עמי כוס חמים. ha-omer l'havero konam she-ani ne-eneh lekha im
i attah mit-areach etzli v'tokhal immi pat khammah v'tishteh immi kos khamim.
So I will not derive any benefit from you if you don't
come and spend, you know, and come and come over and be
my
guest and agree to eat some hot bread and drink with me
a cup of tea. Okay. והלה הקפיד כנגדו. v'hala hikpid k'negdo. And
the other one says, and you know what? And if you don't
come and do and be my guest then you know what all
my stuff is like go ahead, you know, then I won't get
any benefit from you. אף אלו נדרי זירוזין ולא הודו לו חכמים.
af elu nidrei zeruzin v'lo hodu lo khakhamim. These are also נדרי
זירוזין nidrei zeruzin and the חכמים khakhamim did not agree to it.
So
now, now why is this יתר על כן? yeter al ken? Because
this is like the cases we had before which is the reciprocity.
If you don't come and be my guest, I won't get any
benefit from you. Okay. So not only did רבי אלעזר בן יעקב
Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov say that when you say if you're not
my guest my stuff is forbidden to you, that's נדרי זירוזין, nidrei
zeruzin, but even this case of reciprocity, right, that if you're not
my guest then I won't get benefit from you where you might
think it's sincere for all that discussion we had earlier about the
reciprocity aspect, even this רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
says is not sincere and is נדרי זירוזין. nidrei zeruzin. Alright, got
it? So not just the case if you don't have dinner my
stuff is forbidden to you, but even the case that if you
don't have dinner your stuff is forbidden to me, even this רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says is forbidden. Okay. So
מאי
לא הודו לו חכמים? mai lo hodu lo khakhamim? What does it
mean the Sages didn't agree? לאו, lav, isn't this saying that אפילו
בקמייתא? afillu b'kammaita? That even
not only did they not agree in this reciprocity case and they
said it was sincere, but even in the case of just if
you don't have dinner my stuff is forbidden to you, the first
case, even that they would say would be sincere? ושמע מינה פליגי
רבנן עליה. u-shema mina pligi rabbanan alei. And therefore you see the
rabbis do disagree with רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
and they say that certainly in the reciprocity case he's sincere, but
even in the one directional case he's sincere. So שמע מינה. shema
mina. So our גרסה girsa is you're right. Since it says רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov added and the Sages didn't
agree, presumably it means the Sages didn't agree with everything that רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov said. Alright, now there are
other גרסאות girsot out there. There's another גרסה girsa that says no,
maybe the Sages only disagree with the second part and not the
first. This is clear what the first part and the second part
is. The first part is if you don't have dinner with me,
my stuff is forbidden to you. That's more obvious just a type
of trying to leverage you, push you, encourage you, etc. The other
stuff is if you don't have dinner with me then your stuff
is forbidden to me where it's the opposite direction, that might be
more sincere. So רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov said
in both cases it's נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin and then it says
the חכמים khakhamim didn't agree. So did they just not agree in
the second case when it goes in both directions? That's the case
that they say is binding. Or maybe even the first case they
say is binding. So our גרסה girsa is that the חכמים khakhamim
even in the first case would have said it's binding. There's another
גרסה girsa the גמרא Gemara that says no maybe the חכמים khakhamim
just disagreed with the second case not the first. But what is
clear is that רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov
does say that both cases is not binding. And now the גמרא
Gemara ends and says like this. מאי הוי עלה? mai havya ala?
What was the upshot? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דאמר
רב הונא הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן יעקב וכן אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן יעקב. d'amar Rav Huna halakha k'Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov v'khen amar Rav Adda bar Ahava halakha k'Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov. We rule like רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov.
So you could say now what does that mean? So you could
say now what does that mean that that's the upshot? So since
we rule like him implicitly saying that all the issues were debated,
that the חכמים Chakhamim debated all of רבי אליעזר בן יעקב's Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov positions because if you have to rule like him
it means that they were being debated. Okay and therefore it answers
our hypothetical question of did the חכמים Chakhamim disagree? But there's another
thing that the ר"ן Ran says which the ר"ן Ran actually says,
and Michael you'll appreciate this because you're always asking me what the
הלכה halakha is. The ר"ן Ran actually says it doesn't matter at
this stage whether the חכמים Chakhamim disagreed
because the whole reason we wanted to know whether the חכמים Chakhamim
disagreed was to get to the הלכה. halakha. Did the חכמים Chakhamim
disagree? And if so how do we פסקן? pasken? So at the
גמרא Gemara at the end says look if we פסקן pasken like
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov it doesn't really matter
whether the חכמים Chakhamim disagreed or not, right? Then that becomes a
moot question. So if your only interest is a הלכתי halakhic interest
then the first question is moot once we know what the הלכה
halakha is, right? So if that's true that's like the רמב"ם's Rambam
approach. I'm going to tell you what the הלכה halakha is you
don't have to learn גמרא. Gemara. All the discussions become moot all
you needed to know was what the הלכה halakha was. Okay anyway.
But bottom line is we say a broader definition of נדרי זירוזין
nidrei zeruzin that even if it's not about the haggling even if
it's about pressuring your friend to come do it and even if
there's some sense of going in both directions: if you don't get
this from me then my stuff then I won't get it from
you. All those types of things we say yeah that's just like
the way people talk. Nobody really wants the נדרים nedarim to be
binding under those cases.
And in terms of the gym and all that.
I don't know about that but the funny thing about all of
that is what's the end of it? Because so much of the
נדרים nedarim we find
are about things like this about trying to pressure somebody, right? Think
about the story with אביי, Abaye, right? I mean he had to
do a התרת נדר hatarat neder but it was still a נדר,
neder, right? If you marry the daughter off or whatever then then
I'm forbidden to you, right? So in the end wasn't that the
exact same נדרי זירוזין? nidrei zeruzin? He was just trying to pressure
her to do something, right? So I don't at this stage know
exactly where the line is. Any type of a thing where it
is about getting somebody to do something else, when do we know
whether you're sincere and when do we know whether there's three possibilities?
You're sincere and it's binding and you can't get out of it,
you were never really sincere it was all just to encourage them,
or the אביי Abaye case: you were sincere but you had thought
that the person was going to listen to you and therefore now
that the person didn't listen to you how you know you wish
and then you need a התרת נדר. hatarat neder. So how do
you know which category something falls into? I really don't know the
answer to that, yes.
Can you just explain something about the basic principle of? I thought
it was the majority that
the rule turns into הלכה. halakha.
Yeah look I don't know what to answer to that. In general
the rule of thumb is you go by the majority which is
why the גמרא Gemara said how do we do the חכמים Chakhamim
argue or not?
What in the end dictates what the הלכה halakha is like a
lot might have had to do what the practice was in the
field, whether there was
an accepted practice around this. It might have had to do with
which position they thought was more persuasive,
the logic behind the position was more persuasive. It might have had
to
do with textually even if there's חכמים Chakhamim that argue since they're
anonymous חכמים Chakhamim and they aren't mentioned in the משנה mishna that
might undermine the weight of their voice, right? So there's a lot
of those factors. So I don't know what's behind it but those
are the exact same factors that goes into when a פוסק posek
makes a decision. How much does he weigh general rule of well
if the רמב"ם Rambam and שולחן ערוך Shulchan Arukh say it then
nobody else counts? And how much does he weigh well look what
the practice in the field is? Well look at what the גמרא's
Gemara really the פשט pshat of the גמרא's Gemara indicate? You know
there's no real rule about which one of those to give more
weight, they're always in some type of conversation with one another. Okay.
Which is what the ר"ן Ran brings up here too right? In
his opening lines about the יחיד
ורבים הלכה כרבים.
yachid ve-rabim halakha
k'rabim. Right. But David was saying so why not? But that was
what David was saying, yeah. Okay so now let's go. So now
we had a pretty broad category of נדרי זירוזין nidrei zeruzin and
we really have to try to ask ourselves like how do you
know whether the guy, I mean the principle is sometimes you're not
being sincere, sometimes you're just doing it you don't really mean it.
But again how do we exactly know which are those cases? I'm
not sure I have the real answer. Let's take a look now
at the next משנה. mishna. נדרי הבאי. nidrei havai. Here are נדרי
הבאי. nidrei havai. אמר קונם אם לא ראיתי בדרך הזה כעולי מצרים.
Amar konam im lo ra'iti ba-derekh hazeh k'olei Mitzrayim. This loaf of
bread is forbidden to me if I did not see when I
was at
the Israel Parade there were so many people must have been as
many as many Jews that came out of Egypt and קונם konam
this bread is forbidden to me if that's not how many people
I saw there.
Okay. Or אם לא ראיתי כנחש כקורת בית הבד. im lo ra'iti
k'nachash k'korat beit ha-bad. Or קונם konam this bread is forbidden to
me if I did not see a snake that was as thick
as and looked at like one of those beams of the olive
press. You ever see one of those beams of the olive press?
Those are pretty huge and thick. Anyway so okay. In those cases
basically now the ר"ן Ran says there are two different cases here.
There's exaggeration and there's a lie. Okay so the ר"ן Ran actually
says the first case really
מהו הבאי mahu havai means
well הבאי havai means like שוא shav it's like sort of the
parallel of שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. Okay but let's just start. Yes,
well let's talk through the two cases. So the first case if
you said עולי מצרים, Olei Mitzrayim, the ר״ן Ran says actually you're
telling the truth. What do you mean you're telling the truth? He
says well because that's what the phrase means. You know when if
it's an exaggeration then then then the way that's understood by people
you like you know when somebody says we've been literally flooded with
whatever, really literally flooded you know? So if you say oh my
god there was like as many as יוצאי מצרים, Yotzei Mitzrayim, so
people understand that that's a way of talking about meaning there were
mobs and mobs of people so actually the ר״ן Ran actually says
that actually was was true. So the funny thing is then it
shouldn't be נדרי הבאי Nidrei Havai because then you just said a
נדר neder this is forbidden if there weren't a ton of people
and there were a ton of people so it's not a נדר.
neder. Okay you know so it's not so I mean he's right
that exaggeration is different than a lie but but to read this
as a case of exaggeration where that's what it means and you
really are telling the truth then I don't know why it gets
called a נדרי הבאי. Nidrei Havai. It's just telling you a principle
that like by maybe that it's not about the הלכה halacha of
נדרי הבאי, Nidrei Havai, it's a principle that if somebody uses גוזמא
guzma you translate it into how it's understood. You don't translate it
literally. But I don't know if that gets qualified as a נדרי
הבאי. Nidrei Havai. That's a like less interesting case according to the
ר״ן Ran I would say. I mean it's interesting that גוזמא guzma
is translated in its figurative meaning and not in its literal meaning
but it's not a is that clear what I mean?
Meaning exaggeration as a rhetorical device needs to be non-literal so you
have to figure
out what he's really saying. Right I understand that I'm just not
sure why it's called נדר הבאי. neder havai. Meaning it's a principle
that if somebody uses גוזמא guzma we don't treat that statement literally
by נדרים nedarim we treat it by what it's clearly the person
is communicating. Okay but the reason the vow isn't binding is not
a principle of נדרי הבאי Nidrei Havai unless הבאי havai just means
I don't know like airy statements to include גוזמא guzma statements. Anyway
that's principle number one. Let's look at point number two which is
more interesting which is the which is hyperbole which is the lie.
Okay okay or I don't know if it's a lie but it
says like I you know oh my god you know like a
fish story right the snake was so big it was כקורת בית
הבד ke-koras beis ha-bad etc. Now there that's not a way people
talk. The person really is making a claim that that's how big
the snake is. It's obviously just a patently false claim. Okay so
whereas in the case of עולי מצרים Olei Mitzrayim what he is
saying is there were tons of people here he's actually making a
false claim. Okay and he's saying this should be forbidden if this
isn't true and it obviously isn't true. Okay so then why isn't
the why isn't the תנאי tnai binding? Okay so the basic
so so so the answer is is that because it's like a
funny answer the answer is like if you just wanted the bread
to be forbidden it's not a normal תנאי. tnai. A normal תנאי
tnai is something that like like you know we don't know whether
it's true or not you know somebody here doesn't know. Like maybe
we're debating like you know who won the World Series ten years
ago whatever I mean there's an obviously fact but like one of
us doesn't know you know and so the purpose of making the
תנאי tnai we have we it needs to get clarified or it's
a תנאי tnai about the future if you don't come to have
dinner with me. Here it's something that everybody knows is false. So
if you really wanted to make this bread forbidden just say this
bread is forbidden. Why would you have said the bread is forbidden
if this didn't happen and we know it didn't happen? You know
I know everybody knows so it must be you really don't want
to make the bread forbidden. What do you really want to say?
If you're saying right you know there was I saw a snake
this big and I'm if and if I didn't this bread is
forbidden to me are you trying to make the bread forbidden?
No what you're trying you're trying to emphasize the size of the
snake.
Exactly you're trying to use the vow as a way of giving
more oomph to your statement right you know so that's what it's
saying when it's something that is a patently false statement you're not
really making your vow conditional on it. What you're really doing is
you're using your vow to give push to give some type of
a weight to just add exaggeration you know oh my god it
was so big and if you don't believe me how big it
was then the food should be אסור assur it's just part of
your fish tale you know it's part of your you know it's
part of your
exaggerated speaking and therefore that's a נדרי הבאי Nidrei Havai it was
nonsense you didn't really want a vow you just wanted to make
it part of your exaggeration. Okay so that's what's going on there.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנא Tana we תנא
tana a ברייתא. Braita. נדרי הבאי Nidrei Havai by the okay נדרי
הבאי מותרים Nidrei Havai mutarim or he the ברייתא Braita it's a
decided the different גירסא girsa here that כשם שנדרי הבאי מותרים כך
שבועות הבאי מותרות. keshem she-nidrei havai mutarim kach shvuos havai mutaros. So
there's actually two contrasting גירסאות girsa'os here. The one on the side
seems to be the one the ר״ן Ran had but I'll read
the one we have. נדרי הבאי מותרים שבועות הבאי אסורים. Nidrei Havai
mutarim shvuos havai asurim. So our גירסא girsa is a difference between
a נדר הבאי Neder Havai and a שבועת הבאי. Shvuat Havai. The
גירסא girsa side גירסא girsa is that a שבועת הבאי Shvuat Havai
is אסור. asur. The side גירסא girsa is that they're both מותר.
mutar. Now take a look at this משנה Mishnah here in שבועות
Shvuos I realize we only have what four minutes but okay
if you take a look.
At this משנה *mishnah* in שבועות *Shvuos* כ"ט *kaf tes*, we have
the following.
Where was it?
Yeah. So in the משנה *mishnah* it says like this: איזו היא
שבועת שוא *eizu hi shvuas shav*? What's a false oath? נשבע לשנות
את הידוע לאדם *nishba l'shanot et hayaduah la'adam*. You say something that's
patently false. Okay, אמר על העמוד של אבן שהוא של זהב *amar
al ha'amud shel even shehu shel zahav*, על האיש שהוא אשה *al
ha'ish shehu isha*, ועל האשה שהיא איש *v'al ha'isha shehi ish*. נשבע
על דבר שאי אפשר לו *nishba al davar she'i efshar lo*. שאי
אפשר לו *she'i efshar lo*. אם לא ראיתי גמל שפורח באויר *im
lo ra'iti gamal sheporeiach ba'avir*, אם לא ראיתי נחש כקורת בית הבד
*im lo ra'iti nachash k'koras beis habad*. That's our נחש כקורת בית
הבד *nachash k'koras beis habad*. The other one is a flying camel.
Okay. So this is called a שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*. So that
would work with our גירסא *girsa* of the difference between נדרי הבאי
*nidrei havay* and שבועת הבאי *shvuas havay*. Okay? Because that's exactly, listen,
this is so perfect. This is exactly the difference between a נדר
*neder* and a שבועה *shvua*. What is the point of a נדר
*neder*? To make an object forbidden. In this case, when you say
something and you say, and a נדר *neder* if it's not true
whatever, clearly you don't want to make the object forbidden. You're just
using it to back up your statement and your statement where and
that, you know, your false
exaggerated crazy statement. And that's why it's not a נדר *neder*. Because
the purpose of a נדר *neder* is to make the object forbidden
and you're not interested in that. What's the purpose of a שבועה
*shvua*? When you take a שבועה *shvua*, what's the purpose of a
שבועה *shvua*?
To motivate you to do something
or and let's say it's a שבועה *shvua* about the past or
the present, like I am making a שבועה *shvua* that it's raining
outside.
It is to show נאמנות *ne'emanus*.
It is to back up your statement. The purpose of a past
or present שבועה *shvua* as opposed to future one is to back
up your statement. So if I take a שבועה *shvua*, right, that
this snake was כקורת בית הבד *k'koras beis habad*, that's exactly what
a שבועה *shvua* is. I used the שבועה *shvua* to back up
my statement. It's exactly what a נדר *neder* isn't. The purpose of
a נדר *neder* is not to back up a statement, a purpose
of a נדר *neder* is to make the object and I'm completely
totally completely uninterested in making the object forbidden, but I'm completely interested
in backing up my statement. So if I take a שבועה *shvua*
that this snake was כקורת בית הבד *k'koras beis habad*, that's a
שבועת שוא *shvuas shav* or שבועת שקר *shvuas sheker*. Okay, might be
שוא *shav* because it's not שקר *sheker*. שקר *Sheker* is when there's
a deception or whatever. שוא *Shav*, it's patently false. Patently false is
שוא *shav*. You understand? It is false, but שבועת שקר *shvuas sheker*
is like when I'm actually lying to you. Nobody would say I'm
lying, it's just patently false, it's meaningless. Okay, so that really that
really works with the גירסא *girsa*, נדרי הבאי מותרים שבועת הבאי אסורין
*nidrei havay mutarim shvuas havay asurin*, because a שבועת הבאי *shvuas havay*
is a שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*. And the reason it's אסור *assur*,
you know, you could just say well there's a category called שבועת
שוא *shvuas shav*, there's not a category called נדר שוא *neder shav*.
But conceptually, it's because נדר *neder* is about making the object forbidden
and you're completely not interested. All you're interested in this scenario is
backing up your statement. And therefore, it's not about a נדר *neder*,
a נדר *neder* wouldn't make the object forbidden, but it is a
שבועה *shvua*, because a שבועה *shvua* is about backing your statement. And
when it's patently false, it's a שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*. Okay. So
let's just read it, so we have one minute, so let's just
read a little bit in the גמרא *Gemara*. היכי דמי שבועת הבאי
*heichi dami shvuas havay*? What would be an example of שבועת הבאי
*shvuas havay*? אילימא דאמר שבועה אם לא ראיתי בדרך הזה *ileima d'amar
shvua im lo ra'iti baderech hazeh*, if I say a שבועה *shvua*
if I did not see a snake or whatever, מידי קאמר *midi
ka'amar*? Are you saying anything? Meaning what does it mean a שבועה
*shvua* if? Meaning what you would need to say is a שבועה
*shvua* that. Right, a שבועה *shvua* that I did not see. I'm
taking an oath that I saw that I saw a snake like
this, not I'm taking an oath if I saw a snake. What
does that mean? If you saw a snake you're taking an oath?
What's the oath that you're taking? Okay, so the easiest answer would
have been to say that you saw a snake. But אמר אביי
*amar Abaye*, but אביי *Abaye* says, דאמר שבועה שראיתי *d'amar shvua she'ra'iti*.
Okay fine, that's another way of saying it. A שבועה *shvua* that
I saw a snake like this. Okay, so you're using the שבועה
*shvua* to back up your statement and that's a שבועת הבאי *shvuas
havay*, it's a שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*. Okay. So אמר ליה רבא
*amar lei Rava*, so רבא *Rava* said to him, אם כן למה
לי למימר *im kein lama li l'meimar*? Then it's obvious! That's just
your category of שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*. Okay? This is not a
חידוש *chiddush*. It's not, ועוד דומיא דנדר קתני *v'od dumiya d'neder katani*.
It should be parallel to the נדרי הבאי *nedrei havay*. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, אלא אמר רבא *ela amar Rava*, here's what רבא
*Rava* says, באומר יאסרו פירות העולם עלי בשבועה אם לא ראיתי בדרך
הזה כעולי מצרים *b'omer ye'asru peros ha'olam alay b'shvua im lo ra'iti
baderech hazeh k'olei Mitzrayim*. Okay. So we'll stop there for now, which
is basically what you say is, I am taking a שבועה *shvua*
that I won't eat this fruit if I did not see a
snake like this, and
if, and if I did not see כעולי מצרים *k'olei Mitzrayim*. So
in that case, it's not as obvious. It's not a שבועת שוא
*shvuas shav*. You're not using a שבועה *shvua* to back up your
false or patently false statement, right? A שבועה *shvua* that I saw
such a thing, that's a שבועת שוא *shvuas shav*, that's obvious. This
is more שבועת הבאי *shvuas havay*. Okay? I will a שבועה *shvua*
that I won't eat if the following thing is or is not
true. Okay? And we'll just we'll pick up with here tomorrow, it's
already 8:30, so we'll revisit this. we'll start with this again tomorrow.
All right, but again, to me, it sounds like you're taking the
שבועה to give more, as you say, oomph to, like you're, you're.